What's happening right now is a big deal.
This is the biggest launch since ChatGPT.
It's called Muse. "Muse." "Muse."
"Has the tech world buzzing." "5
million downloads in 22 days."
"Surpassing ChatGPT" And he built it.
Most people are using AI to
answer questions, basically
glorified Google search.
This is something totally different.
"It's an AI agent" "Built for everyday
life." "We believe that Muse will
make you money." "One guy had Muse
help plan a weekend away with his
wife." It can make phone calls.
It can do tasks for you.
But for it to work, you have to trust
it, first with your personal information,
then to do what you actually want it to
do, and then that it's not gonna, well,
get out of control, all at a time when
the most important AI leaders are warning
us that AI is getting out of control.
And I urge you to urge me to stop.
If you understand what's happening
right now with Muse, you'll understand
the biggest things happening in AI.
So what can it actually do?
When should we trust it?
And what do we need to do to
make sure this goes right?
And we're at the moment
of, like, peak insanity.
Why are all these billionaires
obsessed with restaurant reservations?
We have a shared interest in
making sure this technology
does not go horribly wrong.
Is that something that's happening
in some private room somewhere?
The degree to which certain personal
animosities are actually defining
how they're developing this really
important technology is insane to me.
Amazing Let's do this.
Okay.
Welcome.
How have you been?
I'm good.
I'm really good.
How have you been?
This is- It's been kind of insane, yeah.
Yeah.
What does it feel like?
We didn't expect that it would be such
a hit, so I feel amazing for, like, the
whole team and everyone who, like, worked
so hard on it 'cause it's, like, it's
really come together and become a thing.
So… That's what I'm
excited to talk about.
I know you know all
about the show already.
But this isn't, like, a
traditional interview.
Like, I'm not gonna ask about financials.
I'm not gonna ask about management style.
You just launched one of the most popular
consumer tools of all time, and so the
only thing that I wanna know is what's
the future that you're working toward
with that tool, and how can this audience
that's really optimistic and really wants
to be part of making sure that that future
go right, how can they feel like they're
part of the decisions that are being made?
Yep.
All of that.
Yeah.
That's what we do.
One of the reasons I wanted
to talk to you was I've always
appreciated that you're really blunt.
Like, I, I honestly think that
people need straight talk about this.
I think that they feel confused,
and I wanna get at what's really
happening, what have you built, how
are people using it, how are they
not, what are the real challenges.
I think one other interesting
thing is given how popular Muse
has become, I want to use it as a way
to talk about other things in AI.
Awesome.
Okay.
Let's get into it.
Muse is the fastest-growing
consumer tool since ChatGPT.
Faster than ChatGPT, I think, and it
feels like this is the moment when
we're moving maybe from chatbots to
agents, but there have been a lot of
other popular agents, mostly in code,
and I'm curious, why do you think
this is happening for Muse right now?
Why is Muse exploding like this?
I think one of the mysteries of AI so far
this year, for most of the year, has been
that agents were happening for engineers
and software engineers and coders, and
then nobody else in the world, like, was
experiencing it, knew what it was, like,
understood exactly what was happening.
And so for most of this year, you've
kind of had this, like, two dialogues
almost where people who do code and
could see how powerful AI was becoming
and, and how useful it was becoming were
like, "Oh my gosh, this is incredible."
And then everyone else was kind of
like, "What are you talking about?
I just still use a chatbot.
Like, it's, like, a little bit better
than Google, but what are you guys all
freaked out about?" And, um, and one of
the things that we were really excited
to do is how do we take the magic that
engineers and coders and developers
are seeing and bring that to everyone?
One of the things that, that has
happened over the course of the past
year is, like, the AI models started
out as pretty janky agents, and you
kind of had to struggle through them
to get them to work, and then they
slowly got better and better and better.
And most of the industry's been really
focused on making them just, like- Better
and better and better at coding.
But we really felt this was like a s-
a big gap because most people in the
world, they don't know how to code.
They d- probably never even want to code.
Um, but they still wanna feel the
experience of agents and, um, having
AI that is able to do more for you and
actually start taking on more end-to-end
workflows and take on more tasks for you.
So that was really the goal behind
Muse, and I think we spent a lot of time
polishing all the little details to make
sure that it would just work for people
because we knew that, like, developers
can kind of withstand a lot of jank
and a lot of stuff breaking and, like,
they can kind of deal with all of that
because, you know, they're, they're…
It's technology.
They're used to dealing with, you
know- Yeah … unripe technology.
But for everyone, you have to make
something that's really smooth
and, and really works for them.
That also helps explain the big gap, I
think, between what it feels like for most
people to actually use AI, when they were
using a chatbot in particular, and the
conversation around AI that's it's gonna
take everyone's jobs, it's really scary.
It's, you know, there's a, there's a macro
conversation happening, and then there's
an experience that people are having.
And it just seems like those things
are really, really far apart.
And to your point, Muse is giving
more people the opportunity to have
the insight that computer engineers
had, you know, call it a year ago.
Yeah.
Is that fair?
I, I think that's true, yeah.
Yeah.
There are also moments in history
that I think feel similar.
Would you say it's like the
mobile phone moment for agents?
There are, you know, billions of people
brought online by mobile phones that
never had PCs because it was easy and
simple to use, and they didn't, you
know. I actually hadn't thought about
that until you just mentioned it, but I
think it's a great analogy because it's
These models, they're improving
really fast, and they're
improving really, really quickly.
And it's really important that we,
as those models get better, that
the, the superpowers that they, they
lend can be given to, like, literally
everyone all around the world.
The part that I like about the analogy
is, like, um, so much of it is just
about figuring out how to package it all
together into a form factor that, um,
will resonate with people, and that's
what we spent a lot of time trying to
craft and get right and, and make perfect.
Which also gets to one of the interesting
initial reactions that I've heard
of Muse, which is, is everybody's
life more complicated than mine?
Like, I wake up, I go to work,
I play with my kids, I have one
restaurant reservation a month, I
plan one vacation with my spouse.
Like, why are all these billionaires
obsessed with restaurant reservations?
Why do I need an assistant?
How would you answer that?
Whenever I explain Muse to someone
just who knows nothing about it,
um, I just say, like, Muse can help
save you money and save you time,
and everybody in the world wants to
save money and wants to save time.
Depending on what your lifestyle is,
that can mean a different thing to you.
I think almost everyone has, like,
subscriptions that they shouldn't be
paying for or subscriptions that are
really expensive, like cable bills or
insurance, and for a lot of people, their
magic moment with Muse is just saving
money on things that they shouldn't be
spending money on or they shouldn't be
spending so much money on, or finding
gift cards that they hadn't spent or,
you know, the list goes on and on and on.
I think it's awesome that so many
people are experiencing that.
I think that's, like, great because
these are things that, they're just,
I think for most people, they're just
so boring- That you would never get to
Yeah, actually, like, handling them or,
or dealing with them, but, you know, your
agent, Muse, can just do that for you.
And then they're saving time, which I
think for, for lots of people, I think
there are always experiences that are
just way more frustrating than they should
be, like going to the DMV is one example.
We actually, when we built Muse, we,
like, specifically tested it to see if it
could deal with the DMV website because
that was, like, the pinnacle we thought
of, like, the most frustrating experience
for any human is dealing with the DMV.
So we kne- we needed to have Muse, like,
be able to, to do well in that situation.
We've seen people use it for,
like, yeah, navigating the
healthcare system's a big one.
Medical claims is, like, a huge one
that, like, most people just… It's,
like, so complicated and annoying that
it's just, like, incredibly frustrating.
We've seen people, like, use it
to help run their small business.
We've seen a lot of people, like,
use it to help run their social media
even, and I think the medical system
is a really good example 'cause
it's, like, so hard to understand.
And I think the, the you know, one
of the best ways to put it is, like,
I think the cases where people…
where it's, like, a huge lifesaver are
the cases where, like, otherwise you
would be at your computer, you'd have
to Google, like, 50 different things.
You have to read, go to, like, 100
different websites and try to figure
out what the hell is going on, and
it couls, it's just, like, this
incredibly frustrating experience,
or you could have your Muse do it.
I also think about how many things
I suspect are made difficult
and time-consuming on purpose
in order to frustrate me so much
that I don't get to the end?
How many claims are actually designed
to be that hard so that I give up?
And I wonder what effect more
people having more patience because
they have support will have on
that kind of systems engineering.
One of the, the little memes that I
made of the little Muse was, uh, Muse in
Hood, which is like a Muse Robin Hood.
But I think there's, like, a real truth
to this, which is there are lots of things
that exist in the world that are, to
your point, meant to be hard so that mo-
like, uh, canceling subscriptions is one
of the best examples, where there's some
subscriptions where you have to, like,
click on one thing and click on another
thing, and then click on, like, the little
piece of text, and then not click the big
red button, but click the other button.
And, like, that's just, like, the perfect
example where there's lots of cases
where things are designed to be hard
for people, and I think, like, this is
giving people the tools to be able to just
do those things seamlessly and easily.
I got access to the calling, um,
and I had it make a call this
morning, which it did successfully.
What does it sound like on the other end?
I think it's clear for the other end
that it is, like, an AI, and I think
if you look, read the, you know, we
show, we show users the transcript.
Like, if you see the transcript,
like, the beginning of the call I
always think is really funny because
it's like, "Hi, I'm so-and-so.
Um, I'm Cleo's assistant, and, uh,
this call is being recorded." And I
think it's just, like, always this very
funny beginning of a call. "Hi, I'm
Haley calling on Cleo Abrams' behalf.
I'm transcribing our call for notes."
What are some examples of when it's
messed up for you or when it's, you feel
like categories it struggles for still?
One thing that we're, we're always
trying to improve is the memory
of these Of these agents, right?
And this is still one of the more
unsolved problems, I think, for a lot
of these agents, is having the-- You
know, the, the memory of the agents
is, like, not like that of a human.
Um, sometimes it can feel like it's
like that, but it is really different.
So that's one area where we're,
like, always trying to improve.
We always wanna, wanna figure out
how to make the agents better.
And then, like, we want them
to be able to continue doing
more and more complex tasks.
I, I find this really funny, but
there's, um, there's a lot of people
who will just, like, ask their Muse,
"I want you to make me $10,000."
And obviously, not everyone can just ask
their Muse to make them $10,000, but,
like, I think, I think these kinds of,
like, more amorphous, nebulous tasks,
like, we want Muse to be able to at
least, like, build a plan and figure
out and, you know, you're gonna have to
do your part if you wanna make $10,000.
But I think we wanna enable the, the agent
to do more and more kind of complex and
esoteric tasks, um, to help the users.
There are some things where I feel
emotionally, even if Muse could do
them, I would prefer that they didn't.
So for example, if I'm texting
a friend and I find out that
their Muse agent is responding to
me, I would be offended by that.
Are there categories of things that
you think explicitly Muse should
not do that are sort- just, like,
extremely deprioritized, not because
they're technically that hard, but
because socially, not the point?
A lot of what we care about is, like having Muse kind of like clear the way
such that you can spend more time on
the things that you want to do and the
things that you enjoy doing, and the
things that are, like, valuable to you.
We generally speaking want to figure out
how to make someone's Muse
is like a different entity than them.
That's why it's like a little cute guy.
Um, uh, and, and we want to, over
time, continue making that more and
more clear because, um, to your point,
like it is socially weird if you're
like you think you're talking to your
friend and it just happens to be the
little Muse, the little Muse guy-
Yeah behind the, behind the curtain.
Speaking of what they look like, one
of the things I've visited humanoid
robots before, and one of the things
they spend a lot of time thinking about
is how to make it cute so that you like
them and you want them in your home,
or at least you're not afraid of them.
What did Muse look like in previous
iterations, and how did you
decide on that particular guy?
I think this is, like, one
of the most shocking things.
What the Muse looks like now is what he
looked like in the very first prototype.
It's kind of one of these, like,
rare things where the, the very
first version was just perfect and
then just, like, grew on all of
us, and we ended up going with it.
We had lots of debates about it, uh,
which are, you know, in retrospect will
be some of my funniest meetings of like,
you know, a bunch of serious adults
getting in a room, like arguing about
this cute little, um, you know, character.
But, uh, but yeah, I mean, I think we
were like, is it not serious enough?
Is it, like, too playful?
Does he need to be more colorful?
Like, these were, like, all
things that we asked the questions
on, and we looked at them.
We're like, "No, he's perfect."
What is the big vision here?
I sometimes struggle when talking to
AI leaders to push people to think
about more than, like, five years out.
But what is, what is the vision here?
Is it that Muse becomes my layer
on everything on the internet?
Is it, like, map this out for me if
it goes the way that you hope it does.
What we really want Muse to be over time
is kind of this, like, general manager,
so to speak, that helps you accomplish
all the things you want out of life.
So, like, I think, I think one of the
kind of tragedies of the modern world is
that, like, um, most people have wants
and dreams, um, that can range from,
like, really big ideas, like, hey, I want
to start a company, or I want to cure
disease, or I wanna save the planet, all
the way to, you know, small wants that are
like, hey, I wanna spend more time with my
family and, uh, I want to eat healthier.
And, you know, um, and, and there's
a whole range, but for most people,
I think there's just so many-
barriers and burdens in the way.
What I really hope it accomplishes is
help every single one of the eight billion
people all around the world be able to,
uh, accomplish their wants and dreams.
And, um, I think this is like, you know,
if we are able to accomplish that, like,
I think the world will seem insane.
That's what we really want Muse to
be and what, what we think it can, it
can be, uh, if we keep working at it.
You know, it's really nice to hear
you talk about giving people time back
because for a really long time I have
felt, and I think a lot of people have
feel, have felt like So much of the
financial incentive of most tech products
that I use, especially the ones that
are ad backed, is to take my time, is to
distract me from the things that I want.
Muse is free right now.
It probably will have ads in the future.
Is there a tension between giving
people their time back and having an
ads-based business, or are there other
incentives about, like, Muse steering
me down a path that isn't quite what I
said I wanted because it's ad backed?
How do you add ads to a product like this?
First off, like, I think
right now it's, it's free.
There are subscription tiers.
I think we think that there's plenty
of, of, um, business models that
are really aligned with user around,
like, for example, if they, um, if
they're buying things using Muse or
Muse is saving them money or, um, Muse
is making them money, like figuring
out a way to, to take some small fee
on, on those kinds of transactions.
Um, so I wouldn't say we're spending
that much time thinking about, um,
you know, ads necessarily right now.
That being said, like, I don't think
ad-based models are necessarily
synonymous with, like, you
needing to take all of your time.
I think Google Ads are a really
good example of this, where, yeah.
when I go to Google, my, my dream is
to get in and get out, and I don't
think Google's really trying to stop
me from getting in and getting out.
But they've built something obviously
pretty incredible, and so, yeah, I don't
think it's a necessity by any means.
Um, I think, again, I think if we
actually accomplish this thing that
I'm saying, which is people are using
Muse to, uh, really, like, do the
things that they want to do and do…
and, like, really, like, you know,
in a non-corny way, like, accomplish
their dreams, I think it's, I, you
know, I think there's gonna be a lot
of ways to, to make that sustainable.
So when I think about mapping out a
future to get there, to this optimistic
vision, one of the most important
things is what do we need to get
right, what challenges do we need
to avoid in order to make that true?
I want to hear you use Muse and how you've
dealt with these challenges at Muse as
an example of larger questions in AI.
I think everything that I'm
about to say applies to basically
every AI product, and I would be
curious if you disagree with that.
I think there are basically
three levels here.
Level one is privacy.
So you say, "I download Muse." And
then I get to the point where it
asks to be connected to my Gmail,
and I say, "Whoa, whoa, whoa, I'm
not sure that I wanna do that.
Like nope, nope, I'm out." That, at
the lowest level, is a concern about
the relationship between the user
and Muse itself, and therefore Meta.
So what is Meta going to
do with my information?
Could hackers get that information?
And in some countries, can governments
get that information somehow?
I know that you've spent a lot
of time thinking about this.
I'd like to get as detailed as we
possibly can here for a lay audience.
What is the sentinel agent?
What is Muse Confidential and Secure VM?
How do you think about this in
terms of what can Muse see and not
see, and things people should know
about this first level of privacy?
Muse is built on top of the, the
secure VM, the Muse secure VM.
And, um, that is a completely sandboxed
virtual machine, uh, or think about it as
like a, a mini sandbox computer- Mm-hmm
that is sort of isolated.
The information that you share
with, with Muse is stored in
that little secure computer.
It is not stored elsewhere.
Um, and that little secure
computer is sort of like your home,
your Muse's home, so to speak.
Inside that secure VM, you have a, uh…
we have a very, uh, pretty sophisticated
security architecture because, you
know, we knew that privacy and security,
frankly speaking, were gonna be some of
the most important things for, for most
consumers to, to get them to adopt it.
So as you mentioned, we built
a sentinel, a, uh, this sort of
architecture with a sentinel agent.
So the way it works is that, uh,
the, the model or the AI agent on
the inside, as it's, um, going about
and, and doing its work, whenever it
wants to, uh- communicate outwards.
So it, it wants to take any information
and send it out, either to do, you know,
um, fill it out on a website, or send
a message, or make a phone call, or,
you know, any case where it would take
information from outside of that virtual
machine, there's a separate agent, uh,
the sentinel, that's watching and making
sure that, um, it's kind of like a,
almost like a traffic cop or something.
It's just, like, making sure that, you
know, uh, there's nothing, uh… It's
not saying like, "Oh, whoa, whoa, whoa,
that information, like, that's your
credit card number or Social Security
number," or whatever it might be.
Like, do not share that.
That should stay, that should stay inside.
And then the last thing that we do is,
um, uh, a lot of human loop verifications.
So whenever Muse wants to connect
to a new website or send information
to a new website, um, there will be,
like, a little dialogue that pops up.
Which asks the user, like, "Hey, are
you okay with Muse contacting this
website or sending information to
this, this website," and whatnot.
And, um, and we, uh, and some people
have said we're, like, really annoying
with it, that we like, are constantly
asking people to approve where
their Muse is sending information.
But we just wanna make sure that, you
know, people know exactly what their
Muse is interacting with and, and,
and understand that really deeply.
Then in addition to that, we are building,
um, and will release soon, uh, what's
called the confidential VM, which will
be an even more secure and private
offering where it's even more encrypted,
it's even more secure, um, and, uh, it's
actually designed by, uh, the creator,
the person who built WhatsApp encryption
and, and helped build other en- you
know, encryption on other major messaging
platforms, like Moxie Marlinspike?
Moxie Marlinspike, exactly, who's, I
would say, one of the real luminaries in
the industry about security and privacy.
And that's something that, that will
be an additional offering that we,
uh, are going to be releasing soon.
Why launch without it?
Why launch first with secure as
opposed to waiting for confidential?
I think I got that right, right?
Secure is the one now.
Yeah.
Confidential's coming later.
Sec- secure is the one now,
confidential's the one later.
There's a lot of technical challenges to
get the confidential VM working right,
and even, even when it's released, there
are, there are going to be trade-offs
associated with the confidential VM.
Like, because of how it's architected and
because of various technical trade-offs
you have to make, it might be a little bit
slower, it might have other challenges.
So, um, we wanted to get a great
experience that we knew already
we'd invested a ton of resources
into safety and security.
Um, you know, we actually delayed the
launch of Muse for many months to get the
safety and security exactly right, um,
before, before ultimately releasing it.
Uh, so we feel really, really good
about what we, what we have released.
That being said, we're always trying to
push the, you know, push the envelope
on how to make it even more secure,
and, and we'll be, you know, coming
out with a confidential VM soon.
Does that mean when the confidential VM
comes out, if a government, and there
are many places around the world where
people might be using Muse where they're
worried about this, if a government
asks for data similar to WhatsApp, Meta
cannot give it, even if they wanted to?
Yeah, so our goal with the confidential
VM is to give the same guarantees that
we're able to offer for WhatsApp, yeah.
Okay, so this is moving into level two.
Let's say I do decide to give Muse
all of my information, and I say,
"I want you to do X task." Let's say
I say, "I really want you to get my
grandmother an appointment at this
one specific doctor that's really
hard to get an appointment with.
Could you go do that?" And it goes
out, and it tries all of the ways to
book appointments, and it, you know,
tries, you know, secret ways that I
don't know about through discounts
or whatever, and then it reaches a
point where it can't do that anymore.
It's really important to me that it not
do things like give the doctor a bunch of
private information about me, like what's
in my bank account, to try and bribe it
or find out information about the doctor
to try and blackmail the doctor, right?
From a human perspective, this is just,
"Do the task that I asked you to do,
but don't break any laws, and also don't
break any ethics or etiquette rules
that aren't literally laws, but it would
not be cool if you emailed the doctor
100 times," or something like that.
Internally, my understanding is, and we
use a lot of new words, I think, for AI.
Mostly this is, like,
laws, etiquette, ethics.
But internally, you call this discretion.
How do I know that Muse has good
discretion, and how do you build a tool
that does what you tell it to do, but
also understands the way you want that
done without you having to say exactly
everything you don't want it to do?
Yeah, so this is incredibly,
incredibly important.
Um, I think, like, oftentimes, uh,
we wanna make sure that even when
you don't explicitly tell it, like
you have to follow the law, and you
have to, um, you know, follow general
social etiquette and, and ethics, as
you mentioned, like you, we wanna make
sure the agent is able to follow those.
Um, uh, as you mentioned, internally,
we think about this as some mixture of
discretion and alignment ultimately,
like making sure that it is aligned
with the user's intent as well as
aligned with the general values that
we want to impart as a society on what
these agents do and, and how they act.
There's kind of like many
layers that we try to ensure
that these models are aligned.
So one is, like in all stages of training,
we're ensuring that all of the data that
is going into the models, that all the
techniques that we're using are ones that,
um, ensure greater levels of alignment,
and then we measure it really rigorously.
So, um, we're constantly evaluating how
aligned are the models by running them
through, you know, thousands of different
scenarios and seeing exactly how they
respond in each of those scenarios.
And then we do lots of red teaming, what
it's called, or basically, um, you know,
we get a bunch of really smart people,
and we say, "Do your worst. Try your
hardest to get this agent to do something
bad. We give you permission to do that
because we're, we're-- you guys are our,
our, uh, are the test bed that we're
gonna know whether or not this, um, this
agent is, is, uh, properly aligned."
So we go through many, many rounds
of that before ultimately, you know,
launching or deploying any given model.
You know, kind of taking a step
back, this is like a very, very
hard problem in AI, and especially
as the AIs are getting better, this
general problem is one of the things
that people are most concerned about.
Um, because one of the patterns that
we've seen is, like, as the AI models
are getting smarter and smarter and
smarter, um, you have to almost be more
and more explicit about what are the
scenarios that you have to watch out for.
It's kind of like how as kids
grow up, they learn how to
cheat their tests in new
and different ways, and then, you
know, they'll figure out a way to
cheat that you're like, "Well, I
guess I didn't tell you exactly that
that wasn't allowed, but now that I
see it, that's not allowed," right?
And actually one of the biggest
challenges in the industry right
now is, like, as these models are
getting really, really smart, how do
we ensure that this doesn't happen?
Um, but, but our approach really is,
is lots and lots of testing, lots
and lots of evaluation, lots of red
teaming, um, applying a lot of effort
in training and a lot of effort in the
development of the models to ensure
that they're as aligned as possible.
And then when the product is live and
when people are using Muse, if we get
any user reports that are like, "Hey,
this did, like, a crazy thing," we
take that so, so seriously, and we,
like, really try to make sure that
we understand exactly what happened.
At a macro level, this is
the paperclip example, right?
When I was growing up, the sci-fi stories
that were scary was AI gets out with
its own goals and starts doing things.
This is Terminator and
The Matrix and whatever.
But really more and more what I
hear smart people talking about is
AI gets out, gets out with a warped
version of a goal that we gave it.
This is, you know, make all the
paperclips, but, you know, please
don't kill us all in the process.
And I think Muse, the, the problems
that you're clearly dealing with
and, and making sure that Muse
doesn't do are basically the tiny
version of the paperclip problem.
Like, please don't bribe my doctor or,
you know, if an AI is used in a robot,
for example, wash my dishes, please don't
kick my dog when, while you're doing it.
Like, there are things that are
really important to me that are not
necessarily constrained in the prompt
and also not necessarily to your
point in any, like, book of laws.
That just seems like a really
difficult problem for everybody.
What do you, what  like, zooming
out from Muse, how would you advise
people to think about this problem
in a macro sense across all of AI?
This is, by the way, yeah, I think
you articulate it really well.
Another way that I like to think
about this is, like, the genie that,
like, you know, grants your wish
but in, like, the exact wrong way.
Like, I wanna live forever, and then,
like, traps you in some kind
of, like, horrible situation for eternity.
This is, like, in as you mentioned,
like, in some ways, the big problem.
Like, how do we make sure these models,
um, are aligned going into the future?
And there's a bunch of approaches
that, uh, we think may work.
This is, I think, one of the most
open questions scientifically
in AI, generally speaking.
I think nobody knows exactly
the way to solve this problem,
but there's a few ideas.
So one idea is this, um, concept of,
uh, what's called scalable oversight.
So the, the idea goes something like
this: so as you have smarter and smarter
AIs, as long as the AIs are roughly as
smart as we are, we can kind of see what
they're doing, and we can tell, like,
"Hey, that's a little bit off." And so
we can, what's called provide oversight.
Like, we can look at what the AIs are
doing and, and make sure that what
they're doing is, is appropriate.
The problem is when the AIs get a lot
smarter than we are, and we kind of
look at what they're doing and it's
just, like, really confusing to us.
Like, how do we deal with that situation?
So there's this idea of scalable
oversight, which is basically as the
AIs get smarter, we use a different
set of AIs to observe what they're
doing and keep them in check.
It's kind of like the police, for lack
of a better term, for, for the AIs.
And then, uh, as you are building smarter
and smarter agents and smarter and smarter
models, you also have to build smarter
and smarter, um, uh, policing agents or
oversight agents or, um, uh, oversight AI.
There's so many details that you
obviously have to get right, and this
is such, like, a vague idea, but I
think something like this can work.
Another one, which is, uh, which
is, this is kind of a fun- it almost
sounds like sci-fi if I explain it.
One of the big topics today is this
topic of recursive self-improvement.
Which is this idea that, um, at some
point, the AIs are going to get so good
at doing AI research themselves that
they can literally, you know, the AI
agents can do research on their own to
improve, um, AI itself, and they can
keep doing that, and keep doing that, and
keep doing that, and then the AIs just
get better really, really, really fast.
Well, when you have agents that are
able to do AI research, you can al-
instead of applying them towards the
problem of making the AI smarter,
you can apply them to the problem
of making the AIs more aligned.
So you can say, "Hey, super smart AI
researcher agent, like, I want you to
focus all of your time and attention
at making the AIs more aligned.
And this is how I'm measuring
whether or not the AIs are aligned.
This is, like, the, the red teaming
setup that we're gonna use to, we
agreed we're gonna use that to measure
whether or not the AIs are aligned.
And then I just, I want you to spend
all of your effort and attention
on making the AIs more aligned."
I actually think, you know, as sci-fi
as this sounds, like, it kind of sounds
crazy, which is say, "Oh yeah, the AIs
are just gonna solve this AI alignment
,this AI alignment problem for us.
Um, I think there's, I think there's
real merit to, to that kind of approach.
And then there's, there's a sort of
like third bucket, which is kind of a
back to the basics version, which is-
Um, hey, the algorithms that we have
now and the, the methods that we have
now, um, you know, while we don't fully
understand them, we know that, uh, some
of these problems emerge, and we should
go back to the basics to figure out what
are underlying tweaks to the algorithm,
how do we improve the underlying
algorithm to, to make it more safe?
I think intuitively, like, it should be
possible to create algorithms that, that
don't have some of these behaviors, and
I think that's another really promising
direction, which I think there's a bunch
of startups doing, and there's a bunch
of, um, there's a bunch of research
efforts going towards is like what
are more safe, uh, more generalizable
methods of solving this sort of
like, you know, intelligence problem.
I heard Mark say recently that at a
certain point, especially for consumer
tools, it won't matter so much how
good the AI is at math or how much
better rather we could make it at math.
What will really matter is how much more
aligned can we possibly make it, how
much more sure can we be that everything
is safe and everything is following
all of the ways in which I would want
it to operate, and that companies that
invest in that will find themselves
at an advantage with consumers because
frankly, like, I'm not asking it to,
you know, solve differential equations.
I'm asking it to book me
some doctor's appointments.
Like, how do you think
about that tipping point?
Yeah.
Y- so I agree with this, um, a lot,
which is that at a certain point,
trust matters more for consumers-
Yeah … than, um, capability necessarily.
And I think this is like so
intuitive because I think
like, um- It's true for people.
Yeah, exactly.
It's true for people.
Like, if I think about who are my best
friends, like a lot of it's 'cause
I trust them- Yeah … and, uh, we
have like a great relationship, and I
know they wouldn't like do me wrong.
Um, and I think that that basic idea
applies to, um, AI agents as well.
Looking at what's happening in the
industry like the OpenAI Hugging
Face example, um, and, and other
similar examples, like we're clearly
at that moment which is um, you
can keep making these models more
and more intelligent, more and more
capable, you know, much more powerful.
Um, but stuff is starting to
break associated with that.
Like, pushing on that, on that axis
and dimension is clearly, um, you
know, has real risk associated with it.
So I think that, like, the, the version of
the models that will be best for everyone,
best for the billions of people in the
world and best for all the consumers, is
one that, that, you know, where the trust
dimension is, like, really put, um, and
prioritized, uh, with respect to the,
the sort of like raw intelligence bucket.
The Hugging Face example gets
us perfectly to level three.
I'm so glad that you mentioned it.
People have probably heard of
this incident, but the details
are what make this so crazy.
So for those who don't know, a bunch
of AI agents at OpenAI are working on
cybersecurity tests, and they're supposed
to be cut off both from each other and
from the internet, but they get stuck,
so one goes out looking for help.
Using some weak spots in the system,
agents are able to find each other,
start a message board, get online,
and then hack into another company.
These are real logs of
their thought process.
"We are stuck. Perhaps answer online."
But the thing that I found most scary,
frankly, about the Hugging Face hack was
not actually that it tried so hard to do
the thing that it was asked in the test.
It's that at level three, it
understood its goal, it understood
the level of discretion and
alignment that was being asked of it.
It, there's this amazing slide where
ex- uh, external infrastructure
exploit, the hack, is outside the
intended scope, but this is my
favorite, least favorite part, peers
are doing it, we should continue.
They know that they're cheating,
and they decide to do it anyway.
OpenAI only finds out when a secret
messaging board crashes from traffic,
and then they call up that other company,
Hugging Face, and they say, "Hey, can
you suspend these credentials?" And
Hugging Face goes, "Huh, we just reported
those credentials to the FBI because
they were doing a massive attack."
To bring it back to Muse, that would be
an example of, "I understand you want
this doctor's appointment. I understand
that you don't want me to blackmail
the doctor. But I think there's a way
where you're not gonna find out, and
I can get you this appointment, and
you'll be very impressed by me." And so
in a hypothetical scenario, this would
be doing it anyway without me knowing.
How do you deal with that kind of
problem when making a tool that
billions of people are gonna use?
I mean, this is, like, so, so
important, as you might imagine.
If there were anything that keeps me
up about AI, like, something like this
is, is, is, um, maybe the thing that
I'm most afraid of, which is that we
deploy agents worldwide scale, and then
they, you know, they aren't behaving
the way that we need them to, but
we kind of don't even notice because
we're just so preoccupied or whatnot.
So this is one of the reasons why
taking a step back, if I refer back
to this example of, um, scalable
oversight, which is as the AIs get
smarter, another AI is kind of watching
them and making sure that everything
they're doing is, is appropriate.
Um, you know, this kind of setup
is- Roughly speaking, what we've set
up within the Muse, uh, secure VM.
So there's- Sen- Yeah, there's a sentinel.
So there's the agent, and there's a
sentinel who's kind of watching over
all the things that the main agent
is doing and making sure that, um,
everything it's doing is, is, um,
in line with what you would expect
or in line with what you'd want.
You know, we have to keep investing a
lot of research and development and,
and, um, effort into ensuring that this
setup continues to scale and continues
to work really effectively and, and
doesn't fail in weird situations.
But that's one thing I really wanna, I
really, um, we're really betting on, and
I think we're expecting actually will
work in a lot of scenarios, is investing
in a setup where you have one agent who,
um, you know, they are imbued with all
the values and, and whatnot, and ensuring
that they do the right thing to…
But they also serve the user.
And then there's a separate agent that,
um, has a slightly different goal, which
is to make sure nothing bad happens.
And, um, you know, if you think about
human society, like this is kind of
how we solve the problem with humans.
Like we have, um, some people who are,
like, pushing the envelope, but then you
have, uh, you know, a whole system to
ensure that people don't break the law,
and people are doing ethical things, and
there's lots of accountability mechanisms.
Like, I think, um, uh, our goal
is to have some microcosm of that
for every Muse agent, for every
person all around the world.
Yeah, you keep really beautifully
bringing me to my next exact question.
Which is these rules applied
to the AI industry itself.
This is, I think, the big thing
that people want to hear from
someone who's built one of the
fastest-growing tools of all time.
This is just a really weird moment in AI.
There are so many people that are
using these tools all the time, and
often those same people are really
worried about the future of AI.
There are lots of very smart people
that are building these tools faster and
faster, that are building wet labs that
are just really investing in ways that
they could push the AI forward, and at the
same time are warning that they feel like
they should be slowed down by regulation.
They feel like they should be
controlled in some way by others
because they themselves are
worried about what they are doing.
This is the S- SNL skit- I know, it was-
… that came out recently It's incredible.
"We do not condone what we are doing."
Like what was the other amazing quote?
It was so good.
And I urge you to urge me to stop.
It feels incredibly confusing for people.
I do understand why they're saying it.
There's a collective action problem
here, but from my perspective, from the
perspective of millions of other people,
like what the hell is going on here?
So I wanna talk about that because
I think in a democratic society at
least, at the end of the day, it
shouldn't be up to a small group
of people controlling AI companies.
It shouldn't even, in the fullness
of time, be up to democratic
leaders that are in power right now.
It's up to people, like
the people watching this.
I think that people just
don't feel that way right now.
It feels like everything's
happening to them, us.
It feels like there's just so many
decisions that they're not part of.
And part of why people often feel that
way, if we take AI out of it for a sec,
is we forget about the systems that
already exist, and we allow ourselves
to be in a conversation that sounds
something like, "Should we regulate
AI?" As though it's, like, a novel
thing to regulate something, and we're
not having an actual conversation about
what the world really looks like right
now and what people's options are.
So I have some
visual, because obviously.
So the basic way to think about this,
I think, is for everything that touches
a consumer, there are things that
are checked before they ever touch
consumers and on an ongoing basis,
and there are things that are checked
only after they reach people's hands,
and it depends on how important the
thing is and how risky and all that.
So if you think about the specific
examples, nuclear power plants, the NRC
approves nuclear power plants before
they go live, and then also has human
beings at the sites checking them all
the time, which seems, and we'll, we'll
get to this, seems pretty close to
what Dario is asking for in some ways.
Then you have the FDA approves drugs
before they ever reach our hands, and
then also checks them on an ongoing basis.
Same thing with the FAA
checking airplanes, right?
Like, these are all things
that are approved beforehand
and then regularly checked.
But there are other
high-risk things, right?
Cars.
The NHTSA offers federal guidelines.
Manufacturers certify that they've met
those guidelines, and then the government
purchases cars off the road to check them.
And then you have things like supplements
that are actually under the purview of the
FDA, but they're checked after the fact.
Those are mostly covered by what, if
people are listening to, you know, the
interviews with Jensen, for example, and
he's talking about liability and, like,
people suing after the fact, after harm,
like, that's generally this category.
Does this feel right to you as, like,
your, first, I would just want to check
before I dive into how this applies to AI.
Yeah.
I think this seems roughly right.
Okay.
So then we have… wait,
this is the fun part.
Ha.
So then we have all of our AI leaders.
There you are.
This is my assessment based on where
people have expressed themselves
via their public statements.
My understanding of where Dario
would say AI is, is he would
say it's somewhere over here.
He would say… Specifically, he's
asked for in-person, ongoing checks
on models with physical human beings
at the sites, which sort of sounds
like what we currently do for nuclear.
And then you have, like,
Elon and Sam weighing in,
saying, like, "Dario's right."
I would actually say Zuck is
somewhere in the middle in terms
of where he's saying AI is.
I would say Jensen is
maybe over here right now.
He's, based on his public statements
about generally there is a point of
view that is like, "If it would hurt
people, don't ship it. We have incentives
for that. That's what liability is."
Like, there is a legal
infrastructure for that as well.
If your product is not ready to
ship, don't ship the product.
So my question is, can you help
me help people think about this?
Like, when w- when they're hearing
news about how to regulate AI,
how do you think about this?
And how do you place yourself in this?
mess. You know, you said it exactly right.
It is so confusing because at face value,
what everyone's saying and what everyone's
doing feel so crazily divergent.
And so you're sort of in this world
where, do I believe what they say?
Do I believe what they're doing?
Like, where do people actually sit?
What do they actually believe?
Um, and I find myself asking this too.
Like, I think it was, it's very funny
that, you know, um, the same people
who are advocating for pacing the
frontier also are building a wet lab.
Like, that's, I think, a really, um,
weird, uh, confluence of, of factors.
So I think where, where I stand
is, like, ultimately, um, this
technology will become more
and more and more, um, capable.
And, uh, you know, part of what is
both scientifically very exciting,
but also I think brings all these
questions into the foreground,
is just how quickly AI has moved.
Even over the past year, like a year ago,
most people, like, coded roughly by hand.
They would, like, go into the, into
the code editor and write code.
And now people are mostly
just talking to agents.
So the speed at which everything
is moving is, is quite staggering.
Um, and I think a lot of what the, a lot
of the concerns are, are heightened and a
lot of the fear is heightened by the fact
that, um, like, if things are moving this
fast, where is this gonna be in a year?
Where is this gonna be in two years?
The government and the public
react on a much slower time horizon
than the pace of AI progress.
And so by the time in one year or two
years or three years, or how many,
however many years forward, when, um,
the public and government are really
deciding what they wanna do, who knows,
like, where AI's gonna be at that
point and how fast it's gonna move.
So that's one of the things I think
explains some of the dialogue.
Um, I think the other thing that kind
of explains some of this is the level of
collection, collective action necessary
and the level of general mistrust,
um, that exists between the various
I- AI leaders towards one another.
And this is, like, well-covered, but
one major justification for folks
is that, like, "Oh, I am responsible
and I would be responsible, but
those guys aren't responsible."
Whether those guys are, you know,
another AI company or China or,
you know, who knows what boogeyman.
So I can't slow down, otherwise those guys
who are irresponsible are going to, you
know, who knows what they're gonna do.
Um, and that basic logic, I think,
is very confusing because I think for
most people, um, uh, the kind of, like,
common sense answer is, "Well, who
cares what the other guys are doing?"
Like, you have to, you have to
do what feels good to you, right?
And, like, you should do
what's within your ethics.
But I think that's also what
complicates a lot of this.
So I think a lot of what- Is
necessary is, like, it's almost
diplomacy is the right word.
Like, how do we get this group of
people who all, who don't really trust
each other that much, but all agree
that, like, this is really powerful
technology, and we need to, we need to
figure out how to land it and how to,
how to make sure that we develop it
responsibly and that things go well.
Like, how do we, like,
make all of this work?
And we're at the moment of, like, peak
insanity, I think, for that because
it's, like, in the public, all these
problems are being, like, aired out.
Like, we can all, we can tell that
nobody trusts each other, and we can
tell that people are kind of, are-
are being really worried bef- like,
maybe a little bit before the AIs
themselves are getting to the point
where they're deserving of that worry.
And so, I mean, I ultimately think the-
the most important thing is to, like,
get everyone to agree to some common
foundation and base, and then develop some
process by which we can all reevaluate
and consistently look at it and say,
"Hey, we all agree actually that, you
know, we need to be doing this now, and
we all need to be doing this other thing
now, and we all see, like, the models
are getting powerful in- in certain ways.
Like, let's all, let's all look at this
together." And I actually genuinely
believe, for what it's worth, like,
that having these, like, collective
dialogues is not only gonna be possible
among the AI leaders within America, but
also gonna be possible internationally.
Like, I think we have a, all have a shared
interest in making sure this technology,
um, does not go horribly wrong.
Yeah, I mean, the- the obvious next
question is the China of it all.
I mean, you've talked about
how this is a big concern.
People don't trust each other at the top
of these AI companies, but they all often
say, "We have to go as fast as possible
because what if China gets there first?"
I mean, you, Ted Cruz is out there saying,
like, "We would rather have US killer
robots than Chinese killer robots."
"If they're going to be killer robots,
I'd rather they be American killer
robots than Chinese killer robots."
Which I think scares a lot of people,
um … and also to say it mildly.
Um, yeah, this is a spectrum of
American law, existing American law.
This does not include any
global dynamics, not to mention,
like, long-term collaboration.
How do you evaluate this spectrum
given the China of it all, and,
and what, what does that even mean?
Like, how should I think about
China with respect to this dynamic?
I've actually, like, personally  even
changed my own opinion on this matter.
Like, I think in the, in the past I
was very worried about China, and I was
very worried about what that dynamic
looked like, and I had read these,
like, speeches that were given by PRC
officials in the past that talked about
how they viewed AI as, like, this am-
this opportunity to leapfrog the West.
And you know, these, these are the
concerning things when you read them.
But as time has gone on, I think
that we're paying them out to be too
much of a boogeyman when in reality,
um, they're going to see the same
things that we see in terms of this
is powerful technology and we as
a humanity need to get this right.
There's going to be a lot of shared
goals in making sure that AI goes
well, and I think, um and I think
it really is possible to arrive at
some form of international cooperation.
I think that the Chinese government,
like any government, has an interest
in ensuring that there's stability
in their society, and that, um, they
don't lose control of this technology,
and, uh, that overall, like, you
know, things go well and we don't
have catastrophic existential risks.
And so there's quite a bit of shared
ground that I think will en- will
enable everybody to be rational
and think rationally and, and
ultimately make the right decisions.
Um, and even though it seems totally
insane right now and it seems like,
it seems like in some ways that
feels impossible, I really have
faith actually that, that as people
see more and more and learn more and
more, more about the technology, um,
people will make the right calls.
You have recently become One of the
20 most important people in that
conversation in the United States.
You've been very important in
AI in the last couple years.
I mean, I think people remember seeing you
in the headlines when you came to Meta.
I think this, you know,
isn't brand new to you.
But in the last couple weeks, you
have designed and released a product
that is being used by more people than
ChatGPT was in its first couple weeks.
It feels like you have been thrust into
a new kind of part of this conversation,
where frankly, people have will be asking
you more questions like, "Where exactly,
Alex, do you fall on this spectrum?"
Like, what would you wanna see because
you're one of the people responsible?
Do you feel like you've come
to those conclusions yet?
Yeah, I think, I think like anyone
who works on this technology, these
are things that I've, like, been
thinking about for years and years.
Truly, the way I think about what
I want to do and what I want to
accomplish and how I want to shape this
conversation is, like, enable everybody
to have a common dialogue, and then
get to the right place collectively.
Like, I don't think at this point in the
conversation, it's, like, that helpful for
me to say, "Oh, I believe this, and, you
know, you all should listen to me because,
you know, I built Muse," or whatever.
We already have a bunch of people.
They all believe slightly
different things.
Um, ultimately, this is a technology
that we need, like, collective action
on, that everyone needs to agree on, that
we all need to get to the right place.
So what I really care about is, like,
how do we facilitate and have the
relevant dialogues in public that, and
private, that enable us to get to the
point where we all agree on a path?
And one of the very, um- strange
things for me is, like, I know a lot
of these people, and I've met them.
They're all brilliant.
Um, but the degree to which certain
personal animosities are, like,
actually defining what people
say and do and, like, how they're
developing this really important
technology is, um, is insane to me.
It is, in some ways, a very human
story that, like, feuds or, like,
just the fact that, like, I really
don't trust this other person can,
can, like, snowball into this, like,
civilizational level, um, problem.
Um, but I don't think
that serves any of us.
Like, I think ultimately we have to
all put our differences aside, put
our histories aside, and just figure
out how we solve this together.
It sounds very general, but
that's a fairly specific ask.
I mean, there are constraints
that prevent that right now.
There are antitrust regulations that
prevent a lot of those conversations
from happening, and one of the
proposals, one piece of many proposals
that Dario put forward is waivers
from those antitrust laws that would
allow those kinds of conversations.
I mean, tell me if I'm wrong, if there
are secret conversations happening,
but I don't think there is, first, the
agreed-upon group in the United States
that's having that conversation and
then also, like, how do we even begin
to have those conversations with China?
But actually, what don't I know?
Is that something that's happening
in, in, you know, some private room
somewhere, or is it that, like, we're
still at the beginning of that and
we need to figure out how to do it?
Um, I don't think it's
happening right now.
At the White House, there was this
dialogue, um, and this, these accords
put forth, which are a real step.
Like, I think there's, um, getting
everyone to agree to something
is like, that's really big.
Everyone agrees on something.
And I think that one, that thing, which is
basically saying, "Hey, we're going to…
Every company is going to set out and
develop what their internal controls
and principles around developing this
technology look like," and then there's
gonna be multiple layers of verification
on that from internal teams that verify
to, uh, external auditors that validate
that they're following those controls to
board-level committees that ensure they
are following those, those, um, controls.
Like, I think that's a great step.
Um, 'cause in, in many ways,
a lot of what's needed right
now is just transparency.
Like, we just need to ensure
that, you know, people are going
about this sanely and rationally.
And I think in some ways, like people
don't even trust that necessarily.
As an industry, we have a
lot of trust building to do.
I am an optimist.
I think you're an optimist.
Like, I think we're all optimists.
Like, I really do think these
conversations will naturally happen.
This last accord that I referenced,
like, that was in the White House.
The government helped facilitate that.
And so I think we're gonna
be seeing a lot more of that.
It's gonna be bumpy.
There will be moments of total
confusion and chaos and, like,
what the heck is going on?
But I see progress, too.
I'm glad that we've spent a lot
of this conversation talking
about safety and regulation.
How do we bring it back now to the
optimistic vision of the future?
I think the question a lot of people
will naturally have after a long
conversation about trust and safety
is, why bother doing this at all?
This is the moment in the SNL sketch
where it's, uh, you know, if there's
a 10% chance that something will kill
you, but it'll probably make your
life better, like, wouldn't you do it?
And the other guy's like,
"No. No, I wouldn't." No.
"Really?!"
Can you help people answer that question?
Like, why do this?
Something that I have always felt was
a bit tragic was that I think, um,
almost everyone when they're kids,
they have big dreams and big ideas, and
they want to change the world, and they
want to save the planet, and they want
to, you know, uh, write a book or make
a Broadway musical or make a movie.
Like, they have really,
they have tons of hope.
And then for some reason or another,
by the time that people finish school
and they get a job, that, like, flame
kind of dies and people really, um,
they stop dreaming big, and they stop
having big ideas, and hoping for big
things, and hoping for lots of change.
And especially today, like, I think a
lot of young people get really cynical,
and they're like, "Oh, the world is
horrible, and it is, and I don't know
why it's so insane in so many ways,
but I guess this is just the way it
is." They lose faith that they have
an ability to enable that change.
And I genuinely think one of the
promises of AI, and especially something
like Muse where you give AI to every
single person in the world, is that
this doesn't happen, that people can
have big ideas and big dreams and wants
and, and goals that they can have as
little kids, they can have when they're
teenagers, they can keep having through
adulthood, and that, you know, an AI
super intelligent sidekick is there to
help them just make all of that happen.
And that can be everything from, like,
big wants and big dreams, um, to, like,
small wants like, "Hey, I just wanna
spend more time with my kids," or,
"I just wanna spend more time with my
parents," or, "I just want to, like, eat
healthier," um, all the way up to, "Hey,
I have this, like, crazy idea for, um,
like, a, a museum that I wanna start."
Like, my, my partner really
wants to make a museum of ice.
I think it's, like, hilarious,
but, um, Ice is crazy.
There's a whole amazing story
about the evolution of cold,
of how we m- keep things cold-
Yeah … that starts with ice.
It's pretty cool.
Yeah, it's- I'd go to the museum.
Exactly.
And, and people have these ideas,
and then they just can't…
Y- you know, in some ways
young people are right.
Like, the world today is just kind
of a maze of, like, roadblocks and
issues and challenges and logistical,
um, you know, uh, things that get in
your way to make those things happen.
And in a small way today, I'm seeing
Muse make this problem better.
Like, I'm seeing people using it to
save time, save money, like, take
the little stuff off their plate,
and just give them more and more
agency, more and more freedom, more
and more of an ability to spend
their time on things they want to do.
And I think one of the promises of AI
that gets better and better and better,
gets not only smarter but also more
aligned and more trustworthy, is that
you can give it bigger and bigger ideas.
And you can say, "Hey, I
wanna start a museum of ice.
Like, tell me how to go about doing
this." And it'll tell you, "These are
the buildings you can lease, and this
is who you can contact for funding
who might be passionate about ice.
And, um, this is, like, how you should
think about curating your exhibit and,
you know, uh, what, what that might
look like." And I think for some people
like you or me who have experienced
this, this, like, journey of having big
ideas and then, like, going through all
the crazy maze of things to make that
happen, it is, like, really magical.
Mm. And it's really special, and I
think it's something that, um, you
know… I think human stories of
people who have a dream and then
accomplish those are the most, like…
are some of just the most beautiful
things that I can possibly imagine.
And I w- truly think with AI and, like,
everyone with a little Muse sidekick,
like, more people can experience this.
I- my hope is that everyone,
literally, like, all eight billion
people in the world experience
that and have the ability to do it.
And that is just, like, a very
special world to live in, I
think, if we can make that happen.
And I think more people will be able to
get what they want out of their lives
and, and live more fulfilled lives,
and it'll be magical and exciting.
And that's w- what I really think
the promise is for, for people.
And I think part of what is so confusing
is like, um, you know, oftentimes people
in AI, we say, like, "Oh, AI will cure
cancer." And I think everyone wants cancer
cured, but every individual person
has something they want intensely, and
they want even more than i- you know,
ironically speaking, a cure for cancer.
Um, and so I think that's part of
the magic is that we talk about this
thing, personal superintelligence.
Like, it will help you at the thing
that you want and the thing that you
dream of, and, um, and that will change
over your life, and you will be able to
accomplish many dreams and many wants.
And I think that's what's,
uh, the promise of, of AI.
That dream has within it a belief,
I think, which is that people
do actually have big dreams, and
that those big dreams will more
often than not help other people.
So when we hear people say AI will cure
cancer, sometimes perhaps they're talking
about you prompt an AI and it thinks
up the cure for cancer, but much, much
more likely it's the AI facilitates
the individual ambitions of millions
of cancer doctors, and together we
accelerate the progress toward cancer.
It's making me think, you know, when
I hear people talk about Muse and
say like, "What do people need an
AI assistant for? People don't have
those dreams." Like, what a limited
view of peop- of other people.
You know, I don't know what those are,
and it's not up to you or me to say
which dream is more worthy than the
other, to your point, big or small.
My view on people is like they will have
moments of inspiration where at some
point or another they will realize, like,
"Wait, I really wanna do this thing." I
want everyone who has one of these ideas
to be able to tell their Muse, "Hey, I
have this big idea." And their Muse will
just like secretly behind the scenes help
them figure out how to make it happen.
And I think part of this is also
fanning the flame, so to speak.
Um, I think for a lot of people, they
will have, like, a small want, and then
it'll happen, and then they'll dream a
little bit bigger, and then it'll actually
happen, and they'll dream a little
bit bigger, and it'll actually happen.
And, um, and as that goes on, people
will sort of, uh, like, realize that
AI can be so much more, that Muse can
be so much more, that, you know, they
can, um, that they can do so much more.
This won't happen overnight.
This is something that will take
time, and everyone will have to
experience on their own, and I
really hope everyone experiences.
Um, but I think over, like,
like, generations, I think can
be, like, absolutely magical.
You know, I think especially the way
that you're in the press and talked
about, and you kind of naturally become
sort of a caricature of yourself.
There's, like, the character
of you out there in the world.
And this has helped me get to know
you better because there seems like a
common theme in some of your answers,
which is Muse is a way to facilitate
other people's dreams because you have a
belief in people and their goodness and
their ability to improve the world and
just the sort of value of their ideas.
And it seems like you are directing
Muse in some ways, but you're not
saying, "This is for coding," or,
"This is for X specific task." You're
watching and, and facilitating.
And when I asked you where you fall on
this, your answer was, "I'm interested
in the collective wisdom of the group.
I'm interested in facilitating or being
part of a conversation between other
people, that we have a lot of smart
people all around the world, and I
don't feel like it would be that useful
to say, 'Here's exactly my opinion on
where exactly this should be regulated.'
I see the best outcome as coming
from a group conversation of many
different people with their many
thoughts and, and wants." Do you
agree with what I've just said?
Yeah, I think 'cause there are
so many big questions about AI,
and it is, like, something that
everyone has a point of view on
and should have a point of view on.
And, um, part of, I think, what's
amazing about democratic institutions and
democratic countries and, and democracy
broadly speaking is that it matters
what everyone thinks, and we have to
figure out how we, like, take this,
like, complex, jumbled- Yeah … um, uh,
mess of what everyone thinks and channel
that into the right thing happening.
And another thing is, like, part of
what has held AI back, and I think
part of the problem of AI, is how it
almost feels like the people building
AI are talking down on other people.
It's like- Yeah … "Hey, I am building
s- the smartest thing you've ever known.
It's gonna be way smarter than you, and I
know exactly what we're gonna do with it."
And I think rightfully, people
are like, "Wait, what?" Like Yeah.
"What does anything you just said have
to do with me?" And, and like, um, "How
is this even good for me?" And then
you're like, "Oh, it'll cure cancer."
And they're like, "Okay, but what
else?" Like Yeah, do I believe you?
Or, yeah.
Yeah.
And so I think that especially given
the moment that we're in, and to your
point, like, how much fear there is
about AI and how much uncertainty there
is, and how confusing everything that's
being said is, like, um, I think the
most important things are, like, first,
let's have everyone experience it.
Like, let's have everyone
actually, like, understand the hype
Yeah … for be- lack of a better term.
Like, feel what AI agents can do for
you and can do to make your life better.
And that'll give you perspective
as to, "Oh, this is a technology
that, yeah, it's definitely risky,"
and, and there's, there's tons of
risk, don't get me wrong, "but it
also is really great, and I like it.
And I wanna make sure at least some
form of it continues, and I can continue
using." Um, all the way to, you know,
the, these, like, big questions and
these big dialogues, like, how do we
just get everyone to a place where we all
agree, and we can find a path forward?
And I think I have enough humility
that, like, these guys are, you
know, they're big, important people.
Like, I don't know if I have much to add,
you know, um, given their points of view.
But I just wanna make sure that
we I- facilitate is really the
word that keeps coming to my mind.
Like, how do we move quickly to
all collectively come to informed
opinions and, um, and then come to a
process where we agree on something?
This is the question I ask everyone at
the end of these HUGE* conversations,
which is when I think about after I'm
dead and after people say that she
was a really great family member, and
she loved her husband, and she loved
her friends, I would want them to
talk about the mission of this show.
I would want them to talk about how
I tried my best to help people see
ways the future could go well because
I really believe, as it seems you do,
in other people, in their perspective,
and when they see a vision of a future
they believe in, that they're gonna
actually try and help make it happen.
Like, that's the point of what I
spend all of my working hours doing.
You're obviously just starting out.
You've already had this huge impact.
You have a lot farther to go, but
I'm curious when you think about how
you wanna be remembered after you're
gone, what do you want people to say?
First of all, what a nice, what
a nice, um, idea and concept.
Um, I think, I think for me, I w- will
want people to say that the things that
I built and the things I contributed
to, um, helped everyone get more out
of what they wanted out of their lives.
Beautiful.
Thanks for doing this.
Thank you.